本视频由Squarespace赞助
This video was made possible by Squarespace
字幕翻译给虫
After this, watch the video I made for their channel More about it after the video
开机场是个很复杂、很有挑战性的事情，很多时候是以盈利为目的的商业活动
Airports are incredibly complex and challenging businesses but, in many cases, they’re businesses that make money
很多机场归政府管，但它们仍以商业模式运作——
Many airports are owned by governments but still then, they’re often operated as businesses—
就和其他公有的商业活动一样
just businesses that are publicly owned
大多数机场赚钱方式来自于
The majority of airports make their money through
旅客所乘坐的商业航班所使用的机场设施
what they earn from passenger carrying commercial flights using their facilities
一些机场主货运，那钱就都从货运航班里赚来
Some airports are cargo focused and fund their operations through cargo flights
但更多的，你可能也知道，类似希斯罗机场那样，主要是从客运业务中盈利
but the ones that you’ve most heard of, such as London’s Heathrow Airport, rely almost entirely on passenger flights
而希斯罗机场中的货运业务
While the amount of cargo going through Heathrow
也很大程度上归功于客运旅客的携带行李
is significant thanks to passenger aircraft carrying cargo in their holds
纯货运航班的数量只占每日650班中占很小的比值
the number of dedicated cargo flights is low in proportion to the airports 650 daily flights
他们每年从七千八百万客流中赚钱
They make their money off of the 78 million passengers flying through each year
希斯罗机场是世界上最繁忙的纯民营机场——
Heathrow is the busiest airport in the world that is fully privately owned—
英国政府没有其任何股份——所以希思罗机场可以说是机场运营如何盈利的教材
the UK government owns no stake in it—and so it is perhaps the best example of an airport built to turn a profit
每年希斯罗机场运营要花费14亿8565万美元
It costs $1,485,650,000 per year to run Heathrow airport
这当中包括6500名员工的4亿9400万美元薪水
This includes costs like the $494 million Heathrow pays in salaries to its 6,500 employees
现在，有76000人在希斯罗机场工作，但真正为机场工作的只有6500人
Now, 76,000 people actually work at Heathrow but only those 6,500 actually work for Heathrow
运营希斯罗机场的公司——希斯罗机场控股
The company that runs Heathrow, Heathrow Airport Holdings
是唯一真正负责监督并管理机场的部门
is only really responsible for the oversight and administration of the airport
而在机场内，还有上百个其他公司在运营
Within Heathrow’s walls, though, there are hundreds of other companies operating
其余的七万人分别来自航空公司、行李转运公司、空管公司
Those 70,000 other people work for the airlines, the baggage handling companies, the air traffic control company
餐馆、租车公司、公交公司还有其他各种在机场工作的雇员
the restaurants, the rental car companies, the bus companies, and all the other different employers at the airport
于是当然还会有很多额外的机场运营成本
There are, of course, plenty of other costs involved in running the airport
每年2亿3200万的维护、1亿1300万的水费、电费、网费
from the $232 million per year in maintenance to the $113 million yearly utility bill for water, electricity, internet
油气费等，最后总共的15亿，就是每年运营这世界第六繁忙机场的总成本了
gas, and more, but overall, that number, $1.5 billion, is what it costs to run the sixth busiest airport in the world
The Kingdom of Swaziland, 斯威士兰王国，非洲东南部的内陆国家
这比运营130万人口的斯威士兰王国还要多
That’s more than it costs to run the 1.3 million person country of Swaziland
所以它们怎么赚钱呢？
So how do they pay for that?
算到每个旅客上，需要每人19美元来运营希思罗机场
On a per passenger basis, it costs $19 to run Heathrow Airport
这相当于希斯罗机场要从每位走进机场的旅客身上榨19美元才能自负盈亏
Essentially, that means Heathrow needs to make $19 from each passenger
that passes through its doors in order to break even
当然，有些旅客赚得多，有些赚的少
Of course, some passengers are more profitable than others
到达的旅客通常下了飞机，过海关之后马上就走了，几乎不会买什么东西
Arriving passengers generally just get off the plane, go through customs, and leave immediately without buying anything
但中转、出发旅客却有很多时间在机场购物
while connecting and departing passengers generally have more time to shop at the airport
零售的利润对任何机场来说都是极为重要的
Retail is incredibly important to the profitability of any airport
这也是为什么机场非常想要尽可能缩短
This is part of the reason why its in the airports best interest to make
值机和安检的时间——这样旅客才有更多时间购物呀
the check-in and security process as quick as possible—so passengers have more time to shop
希斯罗机场从每一笔零售交易中抽成来赚钱
Heathrow makes money through retail by receiving a cut of every sale made
平均下来，机场从餐馆的每位旅客中抽九毛五，从零售商店中每位抽五块一毛五
On average, restaurants earn the airport 95 cents per passenger, retail stores earn them $5.15 per passenger
停车场每位抽两块零三分
the parking lots add on another $2.03
还有其他杂项的收入
then all the other smaller sources of retail revenue
比如租车公司、VIP休息室这些，总共每位旅客抽三块零四分
such as rental car companies and VIP lounges account for another $3.04
希斯罗机场还有个特点是运营一条去伦敦帕丁顿火车站的特快
Rather uniquely, Heathrow also operates the express train from the airport to Paddington Station in London
这样每位旅客还能抽两块一毛五
which makes them another $2.15 per passenger
这样，除了机票之外，机场能从每位旅客身上赚十三块三毛二
All in all, the airport makes $13.32 from passengers through purchases on top of their actual airplane ticket
需要说明的是，这不是说每位旅客花了十三块三毛二——
and its worth pointing out, this doesn’t mean that passengers spend $13.32—
这意思是希斯罗机场从每位旅客身上赚取十三块三毛二
this means that Heathrow makes $13.32 per passenger
这是机场的抽成——旅客在机场实际花的钱更多
This is their cut—actual spending at the airport per passenger is much higher
现在你可能会想，这也太黑了吧？没错，的确太贵了
Now, you may think that this amount of retail revenue per passenger is high and you’d be right, it is
实际上，希斯罗机场是全世界从旅客花销中抽成最高的机场
In fact, it’s one of the highest retail revenues per passenger of any airport worldwide
作为对比，华盛顿杜勒斯机场的值是平均每位旅客五块六毛八
In comparison, Washington Dulles Airport makes $5.68 per passenger
奥克兰机场是七块七毛一，巴黎戴高乐机场是十块九毛二
Auckland Airport makes $7.71, and Paris Charles de Gaulle Airport makes $10.92 per passenger through retail
希斯罗机场是让旅客花钱的专家
Heathrow is an expert in making passengers spend
他们绞尽脑汁让旅客花钱
They use all sorts of tricks and tactics to increase passenger spending
比如，三号航站楼，从安检到登机门
For example, in Terminal 3, to get from security and to the gates
所有旅客都会徒步经过经过免税商店，这大大增加了销售额
all passengers have to walk through duty free which increases sales enormously
希斯罗机场展示板上不显示出发前约45-90分钟的航班
Heathrow also doesn’t display the gate for flights until around 45-90 minutes before departure
这在欧洲的机场很常见，但别的地方却不是
This is common in European airports, but uncommon elsewhere
这个设定可以让旅客在飞机起飞前一直在中间有商店、餐馆的地方闲逛
Because of this, passengers wait in the central area where shops and restaurants are until just before their flight
使得旅客有更长时间与零售区接触
which leads to more time with passengers exposed to the retail environment
而作为少有的，可以直飞六大洲的机场
Being one of the very few airports with non-stop service to all six inhabited continents
希斯罗有专为长途旅客服务的优势
Heathrow also has the advantage of being an airport focused on long-haul service
这些航班上的旅客一般很有钱，所以……
These flights tend to carry the wealthiest passengers and...
全世界的旅客平均会在登机前2小时17分到达机场
while worldwide passengers arrive an average of 2 hours and 17 minutes before their flight
但希斯罗机场这个时间是2小时51分，说明旅客有更多时间在机场购物
Heathrow passengers arrive 2 hours and 51 minutes before which means they have more time to shop at the airport
刚说过，尽管机场要赚19块，但零售只能赚13块
As mentioned, though, the airport needs to make $19 per passenger and retail only earns them just over $13
剩下的部分就要从航班那里赚了
The rest of it comes from flights
每架降落希斯罗机场的飞机平均给机场9500美元
Each plane that lands at Heathrow pays the airport an average of $9,500
当然这和飞机大小有关——
Of course it varies hugely by aircraft—
76座FlyBe航空公司的Dash 8肯定和345座英航747付的钱不一样——
a 76 seat FlyBe Dash 8 isn’t paying the same as a 345 seat British Airways 747—
但9500美元是这些在希斯罗机场降落的飞机的平均值
but $9,500 is the average per visit to Heathrow
这些花费有廊桥、值机区、降落次数
That goes to pay for things like gate space, a check in area, and the runway time itself
机场会从飞机降落次数中收费——从小型庞巴迪Dash 8飞机
The airport charges a fixed amount per aircraft landing—for the small Bombardier Dash 8
价格每次999美元，大到波音747，每次11600美元
it would be $999 while for the large 747 it would be $11,600
对于离港航班，航司要按旅客数量交钱
On departure, airlines are then charged again this time per passenger
每位飞往非欧洲地区的旅客
For each passenger flying to a destination outside of Europe
航司要交58美元
the airline is charged a base of $58
但如果是中转过站旅客，收得会比始发旅客少一点
but this charge is reduced if a passenger connects through Heathrow rather than originating
而远机位也比廊桥便宜
or if the aircraft is parked at a remote stand rather than a gate
总之，例如满载的76座FlyBe的Dash 8飞国内航线到爱丁堡
All in all, a fully loaded 76 seat FlyBe Dash 8 flying a domestic route to Edinburgh, for example
从头到尾大概要交2400美元，从进港、到达、离港
would be charged about $2,400 for its whole visit, arrival and departure
而英航747,的747，比如飞纽约，则要交31700美元
while that British Airways 747 flying a long-haul route to New York, for example, would be charged $31,700
注意这是公开的价格——
It’s worth noting that these are the published prices—
实际上很多航司的某些飞往希思罗机场的航线
in reality, many airlines with significant numbers of flights at Heathrow
会和机场签订一些协议来减少这些开销
have agreements with the airport that reduce their costs
最后整理一下，那些数字最后给希斯罗机场
Breaking it down, what those numbers mean is that Heathrow gets
带来平均每位旅客29美元的利润
on average, $29 of the cost of every passenger’s ticket
所以你会发现希斯罗机场赚的还挺多
As you can see that means that Heathrow makes a fair bit more than it costs to run the airport
公司主要用这些钱还之前工程的债务与交税
The company mostly uses this operating profit to pay off debt from prior projects and to pay taxes
所以最后，每位旅客真正能赚的钱大约是八块二
so in the end, they’re only truly making about $8.20 off of each of their passengers
而这些数字还告诉我们，希思罗机场是希望有更多远途航班来的
but what these numbers also mean is that, by design, Heathrow is incentivized to attract long-haul flights
目前机场容量已经饱和
The airport is currently at capacity
他们每日最大航班数有657架次，当前是650
Their maximum number of flights per day is 657 and they currently have 650
真的没有太多油水可以捞了，这意味着唯一增加收入的方法是
They really have no more capacity which means one of the only ways for them to grow financially
引进大飞机
is to bring in larger planes
76座FlyBe的Dash 8在跑道上呆的时间
The 76 seat FlyBe Dash 8 takes up the same time on the runway
和英航345座747差不多
that could be used by another 345 seat British Airways 747
但让747来却能让机场赚更多的钱
while the airport would make vastly more money by having that 747 land
这也是希斯罗机场飞往英国本土的航班如此至少的原因
This is no doubt part of the reason why Heathrow is so poorly connected to the country that it’s in—the UK
整个机场只飞往英国八个机场
The airport only has flights to eight airports in the UK
这数量和希思罗机场飞往中国的城市数量是一样的
which means the airport has exactly the same number of destinations in the UK as it has in China
作为对比，阿姆斯特丹史基浦机场则可以飞往英国的25个目的地
Meanwhile, Amsterdam Airport Schiphol, in the Netherlands, has flights to 25 destinations in the UK
这说明不住在伦敦的英国人
That means that for the vast majority of UK residents living outside of London
想坐飞机去自己国家的首都，那么在阿姆斯特丹转机更方便
it’s easier to connect to wherever they’re going through Amsterdam than the airport in their capital city
现实就是这样，希斯罗机场是家商业公司
The reality is that Heathrow is a commercial company
就算再多的英国人想飞到他们国家最大的机场也没用
While most UK residents would likely want to see domestic flights to their largest airport
而对于希斯罗机场来说，运营短途廉价航班是非常没有商业头脑的
it just doesn’t make commercial sense to operate short and cheap flights to Heathrow
而运营长途航班赚的才多
in the place of highly lucrative long-haul flights
前者的做法不但机场赚的少
It’s not only less lucrative for the airport
还会让旅客花的更多
it’s also more costly for the passenger than flying to other smaller airports
当然，不是每个机场都像希斯罗机场那样
Of course, not every airport is like Heathrow
不是每个机场都是商业公司
Not every airport is a commercial company
因为，很多时候，运营一个机场，公众就没想让它赚钱
That’s just because, in many cases, running an airport the way the public wants it to be run is bad business
全世界三分之二的机场是赔钱的
About two thirds of all airports worldwide lose money
它们中多数是归政府管，不以赚钱为目的
In many cases that’s because they’re government run and just not that focused on making money
美国就不是像英国那种有民营机场的国家
The US is a country that has not yet gotten around to airport privatization like the UK
美国只有一家民营的民航机场——
There is only one single privately owned and operated airport in the US with commercial passenger flights—
那就是密苏里南部的布兰森机场
that’s Branson Airport in Southern Missouri
与希斯罗的赚钱不同，布兰森机场在赔钱
Unlike Heathrow, which turns a considerable profit, Branson airport is loosing money
惨淡经营数年让飞机能飞他们那
and has struggled to keep airlines flying there for more than a few years
像布兰森机场这种民营的尝试在美国不是第一个——
It’s not like Branson was the only attempt at running a private airport in the US—
英国的National Express是一家运输公司
National Express, a UK based transport company
在2000年接手了纽约北部60英里的纽堡机场
took over Newburgh airport 60 miles north of New York City in 2000
最后惨到又把机场卖回了政府
but it too failed and sold the airport back to the government
美英两国机场民营化的不同在于
The difference between airport privatization in the US and the UK
美国是小机场民营化，英国是大机场民营化
is that in the US, the smallest airports went private while in the UK, the largest airports did
在英国，15个最繁忙的机场中10家是民营的
In the UK, ten of the fifteen busiest airports are privately owned and operated
而15个最不繁忙的机场中只有4家是民营的
Meanwhile, only four of the fifteen least busy airports in the country are privately owned
原因说白了，小机场根本不赚钱
That’s because small airports, in most cases, just don’t make money
而美国的政府运营的不赚钱的小机场
Smaller airports being government run and unprofitable in the US
会给在那里运营的航司某种间接补贴
allow for a sort of indirect subsidy for airlines to operate there
这样一来，机场就会收航司更少的钱来运营
In these cases, airports are willingly charging airlines less than it costs to run the airport to operate there
从而吸引更多航司飞往那里
in order to attract them to fly there
市级、县级、州政府都愿意这样做
City, county, or state governments are willing to do this
因为他们认为航空业是刺激经济发展的手段
because they view air service as a stimulant to economic development
机场运营的公私之争永远不会停止
The merits of private versus public airport ownership can be debated
支持公有的说机场是基建设施中的必要组成部分
but proponents of publicly owned airports will argue that they’re essential pieces of infrastructure
支持私有的说私营的便宜服务好
while those for airport privatization will argue that commercial ownership leads to lower costs and better service
即使在英国公众对机场应该公有还是私有的看法也有分歧
Even in the UK public opinion is split on whether airports are better off public or private
但重要的是，无论公有还是民营机场，运营都不容易
What’s sure, though, is that running an airport, whether public or private is not easy
而每天起飞的几百架飞机
and that the fact that a few hundred aircraft taking off per day
却养活了需要数百万美元运营费用的希思罗机场，这一成就也是相当了不起的
is all it takes to fund the multi-billion dollar business of Heathrow is almost as impressive as the planes themselves